<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="s">Wiener Schnitzler – Schnitzler's Vienna</title>
        <title level="a">Disclosure</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Martin Anton</forename>
            <surname>Müller</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <forename>Laura</forename>
            <surname>Untner</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Wiener Moderne Verein</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>The CC BY 4.0-License applies to this document.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>Under current Austrian law, this website qualifies as a 'small' website that does not aim to
          influence public opinion. No cookies are set and no data is collected. This website contains
          links to external third-party websites over whose content we have no control. Therefore, we
          cannot assume any liability for this external content. The respective provider or operator of
          the linked pages is always responsible for the content of the linked pages. The linked pages
          were checked for possible legal violations at the time of linking. Illegal content was not
          identifiable at the time of linking. However, permanent monitoring of the content of the linked
          pages is unreasonable without concrete evidence of a legal violation. Upon notification of
          legal violations, we will remove such links immediately.</p>
        <p>Insofar as content on this page was not created by us, the copyrights of third parties are
          respected. In particular, third-party content is identified as such. Should you nevertheless
          become aware of a copyright infringement, please notify us accordingly. Upon notification of
          legal violations, we will remove such content immediately.</p>
        <p>The research content and data provided on this website are freely available and may be used in
          accordance with the specified license. We assume no liability for the accuracy, completeness
          and currentness of the content provided.</p>
        <p>All data and content are available under the CC BY 4.0 license.</p>
        <p>Media owner: Martin Anton Müller, Vienna, Austria</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
