<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title level="s">Wiener Schnitzler – Schnitzler's Vienna</title>
        <title level="a">About the Project</title>
        <author>
          <persName>
            <forename>Martin Anton</forename>
            <surname>Müller</surname>
          </persName>
          <persName>
            <forename>Laura</forename>
            <surname>Untner</surname>
          </persName>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Wiener Moderne Verein</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
            <p>The CC BY 4.0-License applies to this document.</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>Today, mobile phone data creates detailed movement profiles of their users. In the past,
          tracking such spatial movement patterns was only possible in rare cases. This project
          explores and visualizes precisely such an exceptional case. Arthur Schnitzler (1862–1931),
          one of Vienna's most internationally prominent authors, practiced <hi rend="italics">self
          tracking</hi> 'avant la lettre'. The research questions of this project are: In which Viennese
          urban spaces did Arthur Schnitzler move? What geographical space did a bourgeois Viennese
          person cover around 1900? Can actual routes and his cultural interactions be traced more than
          90 years after his death?</p>
        <p>Firstly, the project creates an invaluable resource for research on Arthur Schnitzler by
          identifying over 47,000 stays at nearly 4,950 locations over the 52 years of his adult life.</p>
        <p>Secondly, a significant dataset emerges for an exemplary life in Vienna from the Fin de
          Siècle to the interwar period. Significant perspectival limitations exist insofar as this
          concerns a successful, largely wealthy man who moved in upper middle-class circles. On the
          one hand, we believe that the dataset is nevertheless useful and offers connections for
          precarious or marginalized positions. On the other hand, only a well-situated man would have
          been able to achieve such networking in the cultural sector. Schnitzler thus becomes, beyond
          his specific significance as one of the most successful and influential Austrian authors, a
          <hi rend="italics">pars pro toto</hi> for a larger context. Two project tasks arise from
          this: Compatibility with future research must be ensured. Through visualization and filtering
          options as well as map representations, the data should be made as accessible as possible.</p>
        <p>Schnitzler is known as a diarist: he kept a <hi rend="italic">diary</hi> containing entries
          for over 16,000 days of his life, which are primarily situated in Vienna and the Viennese
          cultural scene.<note>Arthur Schnitzler: <hi rend="italic">Tagebuch 1879–1931</hi>. Ed. by
          the Commission for Literary Usage Forms (Chairman: Werner Welzig). Verlag der Österreichischen
          Akademie der Wissenschaften, Vienna, 1980–2000. Digital: <ref
          target="https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/"
          >https://schnitzler-tagebuch.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/</ref> (accessed: 10.1.2025).</note> Furthermore,
          several records in list form can be found in his estate at Cambridge University Library. It is
          significant that these supplement the <hi rend="italic">diary</hi> and cannot be distilled from
          it. Together with the <hi rend="italic">diary</hi>, they are based on largely lost handwritten
          notes that were typed by Schnitzler's secretary. Chronologically, the lists cover the period
          from his 17th year (1879) to approximately three years before his death in 1931:</p>
        <list>
          <item>List of books read</item>
          <item>Dream diary</item>
          <item>List of travels</item>
          <item>Attendance at concerts, theatre performances and lectures</item>
          <item>Attendance at performances of his own works</item>
          <item>Public readings</item>
          <item>Readings in private circles</item>
          <item>Singing performances by his wife Olga Schnitzler</item>
        </list>
        <p/>
        <p>Research has so far only partially approached these compilations in the estate through
          individual editions. The <hi rend="italic">dream diary</hi> was published in 2012.<note>Arthur
          Schnitzler: <hi rend="italic">Träume. Das Traumtagebuch 1875–1931</hi>. Ed. by Peter Michael
          Braunwarth and Leo A. Lensing. Wallstein, Göttingen, 2012.</note> The following year, the
          reading list was edited. It is now also available digitally.<note>Achim Aurnhammer (ed.): <hi
          rend="italic">Arthur Schnitzlers Lektüren: Leseliste und virtuelle Bibliothek</hi>. Würzburg,
          Ergon, 2013. Digital: <ref target="https://schnitzler-lektueren.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/"
          >https://schnitzler-lektueren.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/</ref> (accessed: 10.1.2025).</note> The list of
          travels was processed by us in 2022 with an intern as a trial piece.<note>Peter Andorfer, Martin
          Anton Müller, Laura Puntigam and Laura Untner (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Aufenthaltsorte von
          Arthur Schnitzler (1879–1931)</hi>. 2022. <ref target="https://schnitzler-orte.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/"
          >https://schnitzler-orte.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/</ref> (accessed: 10.1.2025).</note> Additionally,
          Michael Rohrwasser and Stephan Kurz published a reconstruction of cinema visits by Schnitzler
          and his partner Clara Katharina Pollaczek in 2012.<note>Michael Rohrwasser and Stephan Kurz,
          with the assistance of Daniel Schopper (eds.): <hi rend="italic">A. ist manchmal wie ein kleines
          Kind. Clara Katharina Pollaczek und Arthur Schnitzler gehen ins Kino</hi>. Böhlau, Vienna, 2012.
          (Manu Scripta 2)</note></p>
        <p>What these editions have in common is that they evaluate Schnitzler's source materials for
          their information content and, where necessary, fill gaps with the help of other sources. Georg
          Vogeler calls this an "assertive edition", since here, unlike philological editions, historical
          sources are edited with regard to the 'facts' they contain.<note>Georg Vogeler: <hi
          rend="italic">The "assertive edition". On the consequences of digital methods in scholarly
          editing for historians</hi>. In: International Journal of Digital Humanities, 2019, No. 1, pp.
          309–322, <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00025-5"
          >https://doi.org/10.1007/s42803-019-00025-5</ref>.</note> This project consists at its core of
          a Deep Map<note>Cf. David J. Bodenhamer, John Corrigan and Trevor M. Harris (eds.): <hi
          rend="italic">Deep Maps and Spatial Narratives</hi>. Indiana University Press,
          Bloomington/Indianapolis, 2015.</note>, a movement histogram of Schnitzler in Vienna and
          Europe.</p>
        <p>The project work was primarily carried out by Martin Anton Müller and Laura Untner. Katharina
          Sophie Kühnel and Martin Anton Müller worked through the theatre list from the estate.</p>
        <p>Our heartfelt thanks go to Peter Andorfer, Peter Michael Braunwarth, Hannah Gehmacher,
          Friederike Griessler, Carl Friedrich Haak, Julia Ilgner, Eva Kernbauer, Stephan Kurz, Isabel
          Langkabel, Sandra Mayer and Daniel Schopper – your support was invaluable!</p>
        <p>For valuable information about specific locations, forgotten place names and former
          establishments that only locals could identify, we especially thank Martin Achrainer (Bad
          Vöslau), Laura Bahtovic (Berndorf), Hermann Baier (Markt Mittenwald), Michele Beltracchi
          (Ponte di Legno), Adam Berčík (Ústí nad Labem), Isella Berger (Seis am Schlern), Beppo Beyerl
          (Vienna), Roswitha Duensing (Tutzing), Silke Ebster (Bad Vöslau), Kurt Eckel and the Ischl
          Local History Association (Bad Ischl), Friederike Griessler (Reichenau an der Rax), Simona
          Grisi (Gardone Riviera), Tatjana Hagen (St. Moritz), Silke Heckenberger (Berchtesgaden),
          Leonhard Herr (Garmisch-Partenkirchen), Julia Ilgner (Hamburg), Harald Kofler (Gossensass),
          Anton Lafenthaler (Gastein), Johannes Lang (Bad Reichenhall), Wolfgang Mergl (St. Wolfgang im
          Salzkammergut), Christian Nikolaus Opitz (Vienna), Sonja Pichler (Gossensass), Monika Reiter
          (Lunz am See), Christoph Rella (Payerbach), Claudia Scheidegger (Beatenberg), Hermann
          Schröttenhamer (Altaussee), Martin Svojtka (Františkovy Lázně) and Katharina Waldhauser
          (Oberammergau).</p>
        <p>Our special thanks also go to the City of Vienna's Cultural Promotion, which made this project
          possible.</p>
        <p rend="right"><hi rend="italics">Vienna, Spring 2025</hi></p>
      </div>
      <div/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
